[Applause] the reason the reason why it's
the reason the reason why it's
the reason why underst
it's hard to develop because in order to
do it wanted to know what must be
understood
so it might sound like you're
self-explanatory but the point is it's
not understanding takes repetition so
one needs to make the effort of drilling
a topic a theme it needs to be clarified
the one wants to develop clarity in
regard to and in order to do that you
need to know what to look for you need
to know what how to how to approach it
and what understand so getting
information about it it's absolutely
necessary but information in itself as
vast as it can be
that is not understanding and that's
also another thing that sometimes people
would confuse knowing a lot about
something does not mean you understood
what that means specially when it comes
on to nature of things the nature of
feelings the nature of intentions the
nature of experience as a whole so when
it comes to practicing the Dharma see
most people would either just mystify
mystified as in go after after the
experience of the novelty or or some
energy release or something new and then
they will refer to that as understanding
but if you cannot explain an experience
whatever that is to yourself at least or
make it intelligible to yourself or to
to somebody else you should not think
you understood it now of course you
might be you're free to use your own
words so to speak you don't have to use
templates of descriptions and so on but
the point is you will still be able to
convey the meaning if you understood
that experience in its nature and that's
the crucial factor here meaning of the
experience meaning of the whatever it
might have happened to you that you
think was somehow word in your practice
in your meditation or in any other area
of life of the matter and that's when
you realize that most of the time
actually when things you think you
understood upon which you act and
you choose and you live your life you
haven't actually understood the meaning
behind you just do it it made sense or
what is the Buddha said you would be
doing these things a whole industry
simply because it pleases you that's the
sole criteria for most people I find the
idea of this pleasing and that's why I
defend their view and that's why I
defend these actions or I do them work
and so on either way there is an
understanding of those same things and
that's the important difference that
we're trying to highlight here basically
it's not it's not about the experience
that you might have or you might get
it's about understanding it and if
understanding is the focus that's when
you realize the content of the
experience doesn't matter as much as
long as it's wholesome as long as it's
based on the restrained her virtue then
yours is the understanding the matters
understanding of any experience that's
were the results in freedom from
suffering debts were resulted fulfilling
the the practice of Dhamma and and
that's what the Buddha said himself like
when he said whether the five aggregates
when they're fully understood one is one
is a finish to finish the work and said
it doesn't matter so it doesn't matter
what what content of the five aggregates
he would see will say there's a matter
of past future present far near up down
below behind any shape or form it's
going to be within the experience as a
whole which means going to be within the
500 and there is something that a person
has understood so the it the reason
where this practice is harder than to
just sit and sort of try develop
calmness or some Pleasant abiding
through the practical considerations
because he can resolve it will result in
ischl e in in sort of causing doubt
restlessness in your mind and that's
that's how you do it properly by working
through these things whereby you learn
to be imperturbable in the face of the
thinking mind not other way around you
are afraid of the thinking mind because
if it disturbs you and then you you try
to stop the thinking you try to
concentrate on at all on a little when a
little point so you then have to think
about anything else
it's it's it's you who should develop
strength in order to be in battle will
not control the content that disturbs
you deterg-- so it's important to to
then obviously read the suitors and get
the idea as to what needs to be
understood but very often comes down to
that tedious ambiguous heavy drilling
drilling if you thought like like you
sit down I don't know if you read a suit
though that they was talking about for
example feelings and intentions say
intentions you you said only ask
yourself I mean obviously done quietly
don't don't be in a crowded environment
and so on just have some environmental
control so to speak there won't be any
disturbances phones ringing and so on
and ask yourself intention intention
what is intention do I know what
intention is for me for myself in my own
experience when I say intention to you
to anybody what do I refer to is it
understood is it what is it whatever it
is to understand it or I'll just go sort
of float on the surface of the meaning
of intention vague meaning that I kind
of had how would you explain it engine
try try write it down what is intention
and then afterwards read that and see if
it makes any sense to you if he does
then push the questions further so in
this case yes so what is intent what is
my intention like now I have intention
to be seated here and contemplate on the
nature of intention
what is their intention that's making me
do this what is it is it a fleeting
thought well it isn't because I'm still
seated trying to contemplate these
things which means that thought is
present throughout these more particular
actions that I'm doing that I'm trying
to contemplate I remain seated
I still haven't switched on my phone I
still haven't opened my door to the
world so all these other things I do I
do through or on the basis of
simultaneously present more general
intention which is to ponder on the
nature of intention or the nature of
feeling with nature five aggregates so
how else would you then describe that
presently enduring intention easy the
thought this is the some sort of easy to
see it is because if it weren't you
wouldn't be able to talk about you
wouldn't be able to designate him for
yourself left off for others so it's a
it's a peripheral thought it's you're
not see when you're like in this case we
have intention to sit down and
contemplate you're not seated you don't
have to keep it in front of your mind as
in while you're sitting while you're
contemplating you then to keep saying to
yourself I want to sit I want to sit
upon to contemplate that's my intention
no because these actions already carry
that intention that's how intentions
work that's why I keep saying the most
important thing for somebody who wants
to start the practice or somebody with
all the developing is to their full
transparency in regard to presently
enduring motivations behind the smallest
action that's how you get to discern the
the the fundamental aspect of wholesome
or unwholesome bad and good good and bad
and especially to discern where your
actions are routed at because if you're
not aware of this peripheral thought of
your intention that sort of direct all
of your particular actions while in the
news you're not aware of it of where
that action those actions are rooted
that's why intention is wholesome and
wholesome or it can be neutral as well
but for practical sake just look for
wholesome in a horse if it's unwholesome
avoided if it's awesome don't try to
deny it or fear it just just let it be
that he didn't do either way they arise
on their own but your responsibility is
not try to prevent them from arising
your responsibility is to try to prevent
yourself from acting out of it so as I
said even if you're a beginner sit down
quietly semi protected environment
you're not distracted and and pick up
pick up things you're doing pick up
things you want to do bring them forward
to your mind and then think about why
why you want to do it oh it's because of
this this is yeah well why is this this
is this a reason for me to do these
things why did I choose that to be the
reason it's always a new intention is
always your responsibility that's why
the Buddha said every action is
intention you can't commit an action
without having it been rooted in
intention to commit that action and
that's why beings are owners of
direction only you nobody else which
means you are fundamentally always
responsible so it's not negotiable or
optional so you sit down here quietly
ask yourself what is the nature what is
intention when I say intention intention
what am i referring to in this
experience as a whole so we kind of
established it's sort of a biggest
peripheral thought the idea context of
all these little things I'm doing you
don't have to keep staring a little
things that you're doing in order to
discern intention why because the
attention only comes first
structural simultaneous the intentions
and actions through your intentions are
present but intention is more profit
more more mode it's deeper so to speak
it's only to have the intention and then
the actions you have intentions and you
have your environment in regard to which
you have intentions but that's when you
recognize that these intentions
determine the course of my action and
for that I'm responsible for saying yes
or no to it
so we establish that intention in the
most fundamental most basic the most
straightforward description it's a it's
a thought drive thought ad thought
basically so you have a thought that
gives the context to your present
actions but if you're unaware of that
thought means you're unaware of the
nature of it whether the nature is
wholesome or unwholesome and if that is
the case that means you will not know
whether your actions are rooted in good
or bad through avoiding responsibility
for your intentions you end up avoiding
responsibility for your actions down the
line that's why the Five Precepts a
precepts that's where sila and virtue always has
that's where sila and virtue always has
to come first like you can avoid
responsibility only you're allowed to
but not a lot but you you have to start
narrowing down your avoidance of
responsibility someone who doesn't keep
the precepts
he avoids responsibility left and right
and there is no base for them or
whatsoever then you start keeping the
precepts five precepts eight precepts or
more that's when you create a basis okay
I might avoid responsibility here and
there until I would work investing of
work into that and rectified but at
least I will not avoid responsibility
past this point past the five precepts
or eight and so on so that's it just
kind of start rounding up that avoidance
of responsibility for your actions today
clarify your responsibility for your
actions that can then bring further
clarity that you're actually your
responsibility goes even beyond that and
it rests on the responsibility for
welcoming the thought of greed the
thought of a version you will cruelty
the thought of distraction that's where
the Buddha would say the noble disciple
the one with the right view who has
developed clarity in regard to the
nature of his intentions he all he has
to do is not tolerate and not delight
and not welcome the unwholesome thoughts
and all he has to do is not be ignorant
and distract himself from Folsom
thoughts so I mean unwholesome
intentions arise he's aware of it but he
doesn't need to do anything all he needs
to do is abstain from doing anything on
account of it so he knows
I do not welcome this and I will not
entertain this thought to stay even a
second longer if their attitude is
present he is be he will be unable to
opt out of it that's just impossible the
only way you can act out of unwholesome
intentions is if you ignore them to be
unwholesome as soon as you are aware of
their unwholesomeness you cannot act so
it's mutually exclusive you must ignore
unwholesome in order to act out of it
and that's exactly why ignorant is the
most plural word and it's it's kind of
as fundamental prerequisite for anything
unwholesome and also I guess you could
mention that ignorant as you can see now
it's not it's not a metaphysical sort of
secret mystery it's this very act of
ignoring ignoring responsibilities
avoiding transparency avoiding the
recognition of your choice in regard to
the present intentions that signal
ignorant that's why you care it you
perpetuate it through your own actions
if you learn actions perpetuate
ignorance because of which actions are
ignorant so it's a vicious circle but
you can break through it if you start
accepting that responsibility if you
start looking at the motivation behind
direction and then developing clarity in
regard to its nature as I said what is
the nature of intention when I say
intention what they refer to it they
refer to a specific thought or general
thoughts do I refer to mu the feeling
what what is it
the main problem is not necessarily not
being able to give an answer right away
the main problem is not even attempting
to think about it in the first place
which is what most people do because
there is it's so ambiguous initially
then our thinking is used to thinking
about the positive categories things
that are in front of you
so you trying to step back from that
without losing sight of it you trying to
step back from that without losing sight
of it it's gonna take quite some effort
because we are used to just being
focused on the content
but now you have to be discerning the
nature in regard to the present content
so that's that's why this kind of
thinking requires constant constant
drilling and in lots of setups in
prerequisite of virtue and sense
restraint in order to take the route
otherwise it just it just won't happen
you're just floating from one content on
to the other so you can pick up anything
you can also pick a lock the aggregation
feeling for example you can ask yourself
what do i what I feel right now what is
the nature of the feeling how could I
describe it oh is it like this is it
like that yeah but what am i describing
now if I say oh I feel light and well
are those feelings or those perceptions
of lightness and so on feeling is as
this what to say pleasant unpleasant
neutral so all these perceptions I'm
talking about I feel lighter feel
heavier I feel this is a vertical where
would they be routed fundamentally
presently is it - isn't unpleasant or
neutral so let's say I start clarifying
the feeling you realize most of often
most often things we think feelings are
it's actually talked about perceptions
and thoughts and concepts and you will
be talking about those things for as
long as you don't make the effort to
think about what the actual feeling is
so you could see that practice of right
understanding practice of of the
developing the right view
it's not about as I said building on
this this great system they will then
culminate in the release of energy and
some mystical experience through a
practice and effort it's really about
undoing the state of patina which is the
starting point for everyone so it's not
building something new on top of the
state of protrusion is just simply
obliterating everything that makes you
go to Jannah that's how you become a
soda bun so lack of understanding
replaced with understanding means all
the wrong views are gone lack of
understanding in regard to what in
regard to the nature of your experience
Nagata five aggregates in regard to the
suffering freedom from it in regard to
pick up any topic from the suitor
fully understand it you will you would
have you would have been undone your
your ignorance that was keeping you
there was maintaining you a protege
they're just
they just hide work to pretty much so so
in terms of a meditation again you don't
have to you have to start with some
excessively complex topics relationship
between Amuro convenient even on another
loop and so on just just pick up things
you think you know and then really
investigate and by that I mean
contemplate rightly know just think
about information you have about it so
pick up things you know and see whether
you really know that so don't don't pull
any punches don't don't be afraid of
what you might discover but like really
dedicate yourself towards clarifying the
meaning which means make yourself open
to a possibility of doubt which can be
very unpleasant the way you're gonna
deal with a doubt is well it's going to
be self-evident if you had if you have
had your seal established beforehand if
your virtue if you've been living
virtuously and you recognize the
necessity of virtue well they will take
care of the the unpleasantness of doubt
and restlessness and so on but you have
to go through with it so the longer a
person who wants to produce them avoids
it the heart is going to be to do it
later on so you can just just just ask
yourself
about things you think you understood
whatever that is whatever so did I do
you think you made sense
question it or even ask yourself what
you wanted what you want to what do you
want to get out of the practice I'll
give you one piece how would you define
peace do you have clarity in regard to
what peace means maybe I want to be
peaceful what does it mean peaceful
means non disturbed okay so take it step
further what is the disturbance then how
are you disturbed are you disturbed when
you experience things you don't want to
experience are you disturbed when you
don't experience things you want to
experience what's in common to any form
of disturbance the common is suffering
it's unpleasant
if disturbance is not unpleasant it
wouldn't be a disturbance so then you
want peace which is freedom from
disturbance which means peace is freedom
from unpleasant feeling so freedom from
suffering so peace equals absence of
suffering altogether now we of course
that makes sense but by going through
these motions of reflexive drilling you
are actually clarifying it layer by
layer so next time when something
bothers you you suffer on account of it
you realize well I'm not automatically
disturbed by things that bother me
I'm only disturbed when I start
suffering on account of things that
bother me so peace is not not having
anything come your way peace is about
not being disturbed not suffer on
account of whatever comes your way
ultimately sickness aging and death will
come your way that's not negotiable so
these little layers that you will be
undoing through reflection that's all it
matters that's how you practice
gradually bit by bit by bit so then
again other suitors will start making
more sense as well so when the Buddha
says that the root of suffering is your
own craving not the conditions in regard
to which you
that you realize okay so you end up
you're affected by disturbance of any
kind because you disturb yourself nobody
else nothing else and that that can
sound almost were quite blunt in a way
but at the same time it's the best
possible news you can receive because if
suffering were truly rooted in
circumstances or other people's actions
you can't control that you can't even
access that so you wouldn't be able to
free yourself from it but it isn't and
that's the good news
so like the world is teaching it should
be really consider like a like a very
strict form of optimism it's recognizing
the problem and knowing exactly what to
do about it
so when you recognize that the problem
of you being disturbed by things which
make you non-peaceful which is a problem
which is what you don't want lies in you
craving craving for what craving for the
presently pleasant feeling to stay
longer or simply do to stay craving for
the pleasant presently unpleasant
feeling to go away as soon as possible
and craving for the neutral feeling to
be ignored
practically those are the three
attitudes that perpetuate the your
liability to suffering so in order to
stop craving in there are these feelings
you have to learn how to discern these
feelings over there and that brings us
to the point we discussed feeling
feeling what is feeling do I
when I say feeling I feel this what am i
referring to what is the phenomenon what
is the thing present in my experience as
a whole that I designate by saying
feeling I feel pleasure what is it how
would you describe your pleasant feeling
don't necessarily job answering ER I
describe you like this just pause ask
yourself the question let the question
endure for as long as you if your mind
starts wandering away ask a question
again and then try to think about it a
little bit more but don't necessarily
rush into an answer why it's because you
don't want to be producing the answer
you want to be discerning it work
because that present feeling is press
you don't need to answer it in order for
that feeling to be there the failure you
were able to designate it means it's
there but it's your preconceived notions
about the feeling that's what obscures
you understanding its nature
that's what Mullaperiyar suta it
describes that all the conceiving is you
do on account of their recent experience
not before there is an experience so
it's clearing out of misconceiving
zorkin ceilings and discerning it for
what it is if you can discern the nature
the present enduring feeling for what it
is you will be unable to crave it that's
when the standing automatically results
in freedom from assumption and craving